Jewish Historical Society Oral History Project OHP001
People's Archive, MLK Library
Jewish Historical Society Oral History Project
1980-1981
People's Archive, MLK Library
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Washington
OHP001
6.25 Linear feet
3 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Project Overview Materials in this series are general in nature and pertain to this oral history project. Series 2: Indexes Materials in this series are timed indexes for the interviews conducted by the Jewish Historical Society. Series 3: Interviews Materials in this series include master and patron access copies of the oral histories on audio cassette. There are two copies of each audio cassette except for 01-17, 01-18, and 01-19.
Biographical / Historical
Founded by volunteers in 1960, the Jewish Historical Society of Greater Washington was incorporated in 1965 as a nonprofit organization dedicated to interpreting Jewish history in the greater Washington area. With a mission to explore the unique Jewish heritage of Washington as a hometown and as the nation's capital. The Society is the region's foremost destination and source for American Jewish history and engages the community through exhibition, public programs and educational initiatives. The Society activity collects and preserves material culture that documents the story of the Jewish community in the Washington, D.C. region.
Custodial History
From 1980-1981, the Jewish Historical Society of Greater Washington, D.C. conducted these interviews. In 1982 the tapes, bound transcripts and indexes were donated to the D.C. Public Library.
Scope and Contents
From 1980 – 1981, the Jewish Historical Society of Greater Washington, D.C., conducted a total of 26 oral history interviews with local Jewish senior citizens to learn about growing up in Washington in the early years of the 20th century as well as the development of the Jewish community. Topics include arriving and settling in Washington, military service, education, businesses and professions, family relationships, synagogues, traditions and customs, and leisure time activities. Individuals were selected from a cross-section of senior citizens in the Jewish community. Ellen R. Epstein, a Society member and director of the Center for Oral History and Director of the Center for Oral History, trained volunteers to conduct the interviews. The volunteers were Stella Bernstein, Estelle Bossin, Joyce Chaiet, Phyllis Dreyfuss, Tammy Friedman, Suzanne Helfand, and Ida Neviaser. A grant from the D.C. Humanities Council provided funds for transcribing the taped interviews. The timed indexes offer an encapsulated version of topics discussed during specific periods of the taped interviews. In addition, summary pages of topics discussed precede transcripts
Oral History; Judaism; Religion
- Series 1: Project Overview
  Scope and Contents
  Materials in this series are general in nature and pertain to this oral history project.
  - Overview, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series 2: Indexes
  Materials in this series are timed indexes for the interviews conducted by the Jewish Historical Society.
  - Flora Atkin, 1981 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Leo Bernstein, 1981 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Henry Brylawski, 1980 September 29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Samuel Dodek, 1981 August 4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Henry Gichner, 1980 August 7 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Isabelle Gichner, 1980 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Amy Goldstein and Ruth Small, 1980 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Harry Hahn, Jr., 1980 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Elizabeth Kahn, 1980 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Milton Kronheim, 1980 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bernard Isaac Nordlinger, 1980 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Israel Orlove, 1981 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fannye Rose, 1981 January 7 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Samuel Rosenberg, 1980 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Edward Rosenblum, 1980 June 4 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rebecca Safer, 1980 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Eugenia Schwartz, 1980 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Betty Shapiro, 1980 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Leon Shinberg, 1981 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Robert Silverman, 1980 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Rabbi Harry Silverstone, 1980 September 3 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Albert Small, 1981 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Rose Taishoff, 1981 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Harry S. Wender, 1980 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Morton Wilner, 1980 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series 3: Interviews
  Materials in this series include master and patron access copies of the oral histories on audio cassette. There are two copies of each audio cassette except for 01-17, 01-18, and 01-19.
  - Flora Atkin, 1981 April 15 (Box 3, Folder 01-01)
  - Flora Atkin, 1981 April 15 (Box 3, Folder 01-02)
  - Flora Atkin, 1981 April 15 (Box 3, Folder 01-03)
  - Leo Bernstein, 1981 March 30 (Box 3, Folder 01-04)
  - Leo Bernstein, 1981 March 30 (Box 3, Folder 01-05)
  - Leo Bernstein, 1981 March 30 (Box 3, Folder 01-06)
  - Henry Brylawski, 1980 September 29 (Box 3, Folder 01-07)
  - Henry Brylawski, 1980 September 29 (Box 3, Folder 01-08)
  - Henry Brylawski, 1980 September 29 (Box 3, Folder 01-09)
  - Henry Brylawski, 1980 September 29 (Box 3, Folder 01-10)
  - Samuel Dodek, 1981 August 4 (Box 3, Folder 01-11)
  - Samuel Dodek, 1981 August 4 (Box 3, Folder 01-12)
  - Henry Gichner, 1981 August 4 (Box 3, Folder 01-13)
  - Henry Gichner, 1980 August 7 (Box 3, Folder 01-14)
  - Isabelle Gichner, 1980 July 30 (Box 3, Folder 01-15)
  - Isabelle Gichner, 1980 July 30 (Box 3, Folder 01-16)
  - Amy Goldstein and Ruth Small, 1980 November 10 (Box 3, Folder 01-17)
  - Amy Goldstein and Ruth Small, 1980 November 10 (Box 3, Folder 01-18)
  - Harry Hahn, Jr., 1980 November 25 (Box 3, Folder 01-19)
  - Harry Hahn, Jr., 1980 November 25 (Box 3, Folder 01-20)
  - Elizabeth Kahn, 1980 December 2 (Box 3, Folder 01-21)
  - Elizabeth Kahn, 1980 December 2 (Box 3, Folder 01-22)
  - Milton Kronheim, 1980 November 11 (Box 3, Folder 01-23)
  - Milton Kronheim, 1980 November 11 (Box 3, Folder 01-24)
  - Bernard Isaac Nordlinger, 1980 July 14 (Box 3, Folder 01-25)
  - Bernard Isaac Nordlinger, 1980 July 14 (Box 3, Folder 01-26)
  - Israel Orlove, 1981 March 28 (Box 3, Folder 01-27)
  - Fannye Rose, 1981 January 7 (Box 3, Folder 01-28)
  - Fannye Rose, 1981 January 7 (Box 3, Folder 01-29)
  - Samuel Rosenberg, 1980 October 22 (Box 3, Folder 01-30)
  - Edward Rosenblum, 1980 June 4 (Box 3, Folder 01-31)
  - Edward Rosenblum, 1980 June 4 (Box 3, Folder 01-32)
  - Edward Rosenblum, 1980 June 4 (Box 3, Folder 01-33)
  - Rebecca Safer, 1980 June 9 (Box 3, Folder 01-34)
  - Rebecca Safer, 1980 June 9 (Box 3, Folder 01-35)
  - Eugenia Schwartz, 1980 August 13 (Box 3, Folder 01-36)
  - Eugenia Schwartz, 1980 August 13 (Box 3, Folder 01-37)
  - Betty Shapiro, 1980 October 22 (Box 3, Folder 01-38)
  - Betty Shapiro, 1980 October 22 (Box 3, Folder 01-39)
  - Leon Shinberg, 1981 March 23 (Box 3, Folder 01-40)
  - Leon Shinberg, 1981 March 23 (Box 3, Folder 01-41)
  - Leon Shinberg, 1981 March 23 (Box 3, Folder 01-42)
  - Robert Silverman, 1980 July 21 (Box 3, Folder 01-43)
  - Robert Silverman, 1980 July 21 (Box 3, Folder 01-44)
  - Rabbi Harry Silverstone, 1980 September 3 (Box 3, Folder 01-45)
  - Albert Small, 1981 August 13 (Box 3, Folder 01-46)
  - Rose Taishoff, 1981 March 18 (Box 3, Folder 01-47)
  - Rose Taishoff, 1981 March 18 (Box 3, Folder 01-48)
  - Harry S. Wender, 1980 September 30 (Box 3, Folder 01-49)
  - Harry S. Wender, 1980 September 30 (Box 3, Folder 01-50)
  - Harry S. Wender, 1980 September 30 (Box 3, Folder 01-51)
  - Harry S. Wender, 1980 September 30 (Box 3, Folder 01-52)
  - Morton Wilner, 1980 September 15 (Box 3, Folder 01-53)
  - Morton Wilner, 1980 September 15 (Box 3, Folder 01-54)